Guide to the Beatrice Wood Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Beatrice Wood papers
1954-1997
1960-1987
YCAL MSS 294
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9
(10 boxes)
Collection consists of originals and typescripts of correspondence, writings, drawings, and other papers, and documents aspects of the life and work of Beatrice Wood.
Wood, Beatrice, 1893-1998
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Francis Naumann in 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Beatrice Wood (1893-1998)
Beatrice Wood was an American artist and ceramist.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, drawings, and other papers, and documents the relationship between Beatrice Wood and Ram Pravesh Singh and aspects of her work as an artist. Correspondence consists of originals and copies of letters between Wood and Singh, as well as a small amount of correspondence with others. Writings include drafts and manuscripts of A Hindu in the Bed, Just Call Me Darling, In America We Meet, and other unidentified writings. Also found are drawings in pencil, pastel, and watercolor, and two sketchbooks. Other papers include a photograph from Wood's 105th birthday party, notes, and valentine cards.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; III. Other Papers; and IV. Drawings. This organization is largely based on format.
Artists, American -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works); Pastels; Watercolors (paintings); Siṃha, Rāmapraveśa, 1949-; Wood, Beatrice, 1893-1998
- Correspondence, 1960-1983; Series I
  - Singh, Ram Pravesh, 1962-1971; 86 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This group of correspondence consists of original letters from Ram Pravesh Singh, which were originally housed together in plastic sleeves.
  - Singh, Ram Pravesh and others, 1960-1983; 51 (Box 2–4)
    This group of correspondence includes typescript copies and some originals of letters to and from Ram Pravesh Singh, and other correspondence, which were originally housed together in file folders.
- Writings, Series II
  - Notes, 1976 (Box 5)
  - "A Hindu in the Bed", undated; 17 (Box 5)
  - "A Hindu in the Bed", edited and final, 1975; 6 (Box 6)
  - "Just Call Me Darling" (Box 6)
  - "In America We Meet" (Box 6)
  - Photocopy of a manuscript, 3 (Box 6)
  - Duplicates, 1979; 6 (Box 6)
  - Duplicates beginning India "B" (Box 6)
  - Duplicates (Box 6)
- Other Papers, Series III
  - Photograph, Beatrice Wood's 105th Birthday (Box 6)
  - Photographs, Beatrice Wood, James Cameron, Gloria Steward and others, 1997 March (Box 6)
  - Notes about the papers (Box 6)
  - Valentine cards (Box 6)
- Drawings, Series IV
  - "He made only two...so God laughed", 1979 (Box 7)
  - Untitled (woman with stick figure by her face) (Box 7)
  - "In spite of rewarding activity my mind kept going" (Box 7)
  - "Entering the dining room I found beautiful women with powdered [breasts?]" (Box 8)
  - Untitled (woman's face), 1954 (Box 8)
  - "Pendant quelle dire dans une petite maison de [...?]", 1954 (Box 8)
  - "The man who was cross", 1981 (Box 8)
  - "The quarrel", 1980 (Box 8)
  - "Another quarrel", 1987 (Box 8)
  - "She got him to cook", 1980 (Box 8)
  - "Sexual mix-up", 1987 (Box 8)
  - "The wrong moment", 1978 (Box 8)
  - "He bragged of his infidelities", 1978 (Box 8)
  - "Argument at breakfast", 1982 (Box 8)
  - "A married man", 1977 (Box 8)
  - "Conversation between two men", 1980 (Box 8)
  - "2=", 1986 (Box 8)
  - "Don't answer back" (Box 8)
  - "If only he would rape", 1975 (Box 8)
  - "Hurry, there is a knock at the door", 1978 (Box 8)
  - Untitled (story with drawings), 1981 (Box 8)
  - "The boss" (removed from frame), 1990 (Box 8)
  - "Reading" (Box 9)
  - "Kiss Andre" (Box 9)
  - "The quarrel" (Box 9)
  - "Penser" (Box 9)
  - "The night he was out late", 1981 (Box 9)
  - "He wanted to see what was in the letter", 1982 (Box 9)
  - "Sleepless nights", 1983 (Box 9)
  - Untitled (figures of a man and woman) (Box 9)
  - "For the second time in my life I entered a marriage in name only" (Box 9)
  - "Where have you been?", 1979 (Box 9)
  - "Sunday Reiki", 1979 (Box 9)
  - "Peeping Tom" (Box 9)
  - "Outing with wife", 1977 (Box 9)
  - "Meeting of the minds", 1977 (Box 9)
  - Sketchbooks, 1997, undated; (2 items) (Box 10)